<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Ulteo Open Virtual Desktop v@VERSION@</title>
    <subtitle>Administration Console guide</subtitle>
    <graphic fileref="img/ovd.png" align="center"/>

    <copyright>
      <year>@YEAR@</year>
      <holder>Ulteo SAS - <ulink url="http://www.ulteo.com" /></holder>
    </copyright>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>
    Ulteo OVD is configured by a web interface
    called <emphasis role="strong">Administration Console</emphasis>
    or just <emphasis role="strong">console</emphasis>.  It is
    installed on and part of the Ulteo Session Manager.
  </para>
  <para>
    This documentation describes the features available on the console
    from the main menu, page per page.
  </para>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>Console main page</screeninfo>
    <graphic fileref="img/sm_admin_main.png"></graphic>
  </screenshot>


  <section>
    <title>Log into the console</title>

    <para>
      As you probably noticed at installation time, the console is
      available using a web browser by entering the following
      URL <ulink>http://ip.or.host/ovd/admin/</ulink> where
      <emphasis>ip.or.host</emphasis> is the name or IP address of the
      machine where you installed the Session Manager.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Console admin login</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="img/sm_www_admin_login.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      You can log in with the admin account. You can also log in with
      OVD users if you priorly authorized them, as we'll see later in
      that documentation.
    </para>

    <para>
      Once logged in, you are redirected to the main page. This page is
      just a shortcut to some system information. Let's follow the menu.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Server Management</title>
    <para>
      This category is about Application Servers (ApS) management. 
      It includes the <emphasis>Shared Folders</emphasis> page.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Servers page</title>

      <para>
        In the first page, you can see the list of Application
        Server that are plugged to your Session Manager and additional details.
      </para>

      <para>
        By clicking the FQDN link or 
        the <emphasis>Manage</emphasis> button, you enter 
        a <emphasis>manage</emphasis> page that provides full details for
        a specific server.
      </para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Servers page</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="img/admin-console/servers.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

      <simplesect>
        <title>Specific server management</title>
       
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Number of available sessions on this
                server:</emphasis> This value is not a limit for each
                Application Server. It's a value used by the load
                balancer, as we'll see later.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Redirection name of that
                server:</emphasis> this is used to launch
                sessions. When you launch a session, you are redirected
                to an Application Server using the redirection name as
                redirection. In some cases, the default redirection
                name (the FQDN you provided during the ApS installation) is
                not valid. For instance, if you setup a private IP
                address and want to connect from Internet.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The maintenance/production box is a status information. This status is
              used to keep some servers online and ready to use on
              maintenance to be sure that no sessions are going to be
              started. For instance, it's useful when perfoming a software upgrade.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
          For Linux application, it's possible to install additional
          applications directly from the console by entering a package
          name.  It's also possible to ask for a global upgrade. It
          will perform an applications and Ulteo software upgrade for
          security and bugfixes.
        </para>
      </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Unregistered servers page</title>

      <para>
	An Application server is unregistered
	until an admin registers it by clicking
	the <emphasis>register button</emphasis>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tasks page</title>

      <para>
        At the moment, it is only available for Linux servers. A task is a
        request to an Application Server to install or remove an
        application as we talked in the servers page.
      </para>

      <para>
        This page is listing known tasks and their status.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Shared folders page</title>

      <para>
        Shared folders is a feature that allows members of same user groups
        to work together on a virtual drive.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            First, create a new folder
          </para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>Create a share folder</screeninfo>
            <graphic fileref="img/admin-console/sharedfolder1.png"></graphic>
          </screenshot>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Then click on it
          </para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>select the shared folder</screeninfo>
            <graphic fileref="img/admin-console/sharedfolder2.png"></graphic>
          </screenshot>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            And authorize some users groups to acces on it
          </para>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>authorize users groups to the shared folder</screeninfo>
            <graphic fileref="img/admin-console/sharedfolder3.png"></graphic>
          </screenshot>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <important>
        <para>
          In order to enjoy that feature, you have to choose the
          "Internal webDAV" filesystem for user's data. In order to do
          that, click the "Enable Internal WebDAV filesystem" button
          in the Shared Folders page. Using shared folders on other
          filesystems is planned for future versions.
        </para>
      </important>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Users</title>
    <para>
      This category is about users and the user groups.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each user is shown with his login, his display name, his user ID (uid) and
      all other extra fields from the user database.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can get more information about a User either by clicking
      the <emphasis>Manage</emphasis> button or by clicking the
      user login hyperlink.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Users page</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="img/admin-console/users.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <section>
      <title>Manage a user</title>
      <para>
	On this page, you can modify each user attribute if the user database is writable. 
	At the moment only the MySQL module is writable.
      </para>
      <para>
	The list of user groups that contain this user and the list of
	active sessions for this user are already shown.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>User Group Management</title>
      <para>
	This page provides a list of user group with their name, their
	description and their status and corresponding action (Enable or Block).  Also can you
	add and remove user groups.
      </para>

      <para>
	The Manage page of a specific group lets you change status and
	description for that group.  It's also possible to add or remove users from a
	specific group and view the list of publications for a
	specific group.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Application Management</title>
    <para>
      This page provides the list of applications that are (physically)
      installed on Application Servers.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each application is shown with his name, his description and his
      type (Linux or Windows).
    </para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Applications page</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="img/admin-console/applications.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      You can have more information about an application either by
      clicking the <emphasis>Manage</emphasis> button or by clicking
      on application name hyperlink.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Manage an application</title>
      <para>
	In this part, managing applications means that you can either install/uninstall this
	application on online servers, or add/remove them from application groups.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Application group management</title>
      <para>
	This page provides a list of application groups with their
	name, their description and their status and corresponding action (Enable or Block).
	You can also add and remove application groups.
      </para>

      <para>
	The manage page of a specific group lets you change their status
	and description.  It's also possible to add or remove
	users from a specific group and view the list of publications
	for a specific group.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Static applications page</title>
      <para>
        Static applications are applications that have not been detected
	automatically on an Application Server.
        It's set directly on the console. For instance, it could be a "Web
	application".
      </para>
    </section>


    <section>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <para>
	This page shows associations between user groups and
	application groups. A publication wizard is available to make
	the process more simple.
      </para>
      <para>
	The publication wizard consists of 3 main steps:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>selection of users</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>selection of applications</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>confirmations</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
	If you choose users from the user list instead of an existing
	user group, the system is going to ask you for a user group
	name and description. It's the same for selecting applications.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Configuration</title>
    <para>
      At this page, you can configure your sesion manager.
    </para>
    <para>
      Be careful when you change those settings: on some actions it can break active
      sessions.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Configuration page</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="img/admin-console/configuration.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <section>
      <title>Database settings page</title>
      <para>
        On this page, it's possible to change settings for the
	MySQL database used by the OVD.
      </para>
      <important>
        <para>
          Be careful if you change settings on this page: on some actions you can break your
          system, delete your users groups or other important settings.
        </para>
      </important>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>System settings page</title>
      <para>
        On this page, it's possible to customize the language used for the
        console.
        Here it's also possible to change the admin policy for OVD users.
      </para>

      <section>
        <title>Policy</title>
        <para>
          By modifying the policy, you authorize each of your OVD
          users to perform some admin actions. This default policy can 
          be overriden by customizing the policy for a specific user group.
        </para>
        <para>
          For instance, if you select <emphasis>user admin
          panel</emphasis>, you allow each OVD users to log into
          the administration console.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>
            We advise to leave all fields of the default policy on "disabled".
          </para>
          </note>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Server settings page</title>
      <para>
        This page is about Application servers settings
      </para>

      <simplesect>
        <title>Load balancing</title>
        <para>
          The load balancing feature is used to choose which server must be selected when
          a user is requesting a new session. It's possible to customize the
          algorithm to change the priority of criterions.
        </para>
      </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Profile settings page</title>
      <para>
        The Ulteo OVD can be plugged to LDAP or Active Directory, or use
        its own local database.
      </para>
    </section>


    <section>
      <title>Session Configuration</title>
      <para>
        This part is about the default configuration for sessions
        and what the user can force.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Events Configuration</title>
      <para>
        In this page, you can provide and email adress to receive and alert when
        an event occurs.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Web interface settings page</title>
      <para>
        This page is about the configuration of the Ulteo OVD main
        page (the one the user is using to start a session).
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Status Category</title>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Status page</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="img/admin-console/status.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <section>
      <title>Session page</title>
      <para>
	This page shows a list of active sessions with the following information:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="strong">Session:</emphasis> the session id</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="strong">Server:</emphasis> the server where the session is running</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="strong">User:</emphasis> the user who started the session</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
	It's possible to end a session by clicking the <emphasis>Kill</emphasis> button.
      </para>

      <para>
	You can have more information about a session by clicking on the corresponding session id.
      </para>

      <section>
	<title>Manage a session</title>
	<para>
	  On the general page, there are two additional features:
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>The date when the session started</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>A button to join the session using the desktop sharing system</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
      </section>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Logs page</title>
    <para>
      This page shows the log on the Session Manager. The log level
      depends on the configuration set in the Configuration System
      settings page.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reporting page</title>
    <para>
      This page give you a report of you OVD infrastructure in a time
      window you select.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Summary page</title>
    <para>
      Ths summary page shows all links between user, user groups,
      applications, application groups and servers.
    </para>
    <para>
      This page is very useful in the case you would be lost in publications
      or if you don't know why you can't start sessions.
    </para>
    <important>
      <para>
        This page can take time to load if you have many users in your
        database. Use it carrefully.
      </para>
    </important>
  </section>
  </section>
  <xi:include href="colophon.xml" />
</article>
