<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Ulteo Open Virtual Desktop</title>
    <subtitle>Administration Console</subtitle>
    <graphic fileref="img/ovd.png" align="center"/>

    <copyright>
      <year>2008</year>
      <year>2009</year>
      <holder>Ulteo SAS</holder>
    </copyright>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>
    Ulteo OVD is configured by a web interface installed on the
    Session Manager called <emphasis role="strong">Administration
    Console</emphasis> or just <emphasis role="strong">console</emphasis>.
  </para>
  <para>
    This documentation explain the features pages by pages following
    the menu.
<!--    The first section of the documentation is going to explain features pages per pages.
    The second section will explain each features in particular.
-->
  </para>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>Console main page</screeninfo>
    <graphic fileref="img/sm_admin_main.png"></graphic>
  </screenshot>


  <section>
    <title>Log into the console</title>

    <para>
      As you saw at the installation, the console is available using a
      web browser and typing the
      url <ulink>http://ip.or.host/sessionmanager/admin/</ulink> where
      <emphasis>ip.or.host</emphasis> is the name or IP adress of the
      machine you installed your Session Manager.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Console admin login</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="img/sm_www_admin_login.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      You can login with the admin account. You can also login with OVD users if you
      authorized to do that as we'll see later.
    </para>

    <para>
      Once logged, you are redirected to the main page. This page is
      just shortcut and link to some informations about the
      system. Let's following the menu.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Server Management</title>
    <para>
      This category is about the application servers management. It's
      also include the <emphasis>Shared Folders</emphasis> page.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Servers page</title>

      <para>
        In the first page, you can see the list of Application
        Server plugged to your Session Manager with some details.
      </para>

      <para>
        By clicking on the FQDN link or on
        the <emphasis>Manage</emphasis> button, you enter in
        a <emphasis>manage</emphasis> page that give full details on
        a specific server.
      </para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Servers page</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="img/admin-console/servers.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

      <simplesect>
        <title>Specific server managment</title>
       
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Number of available sessions on this
                server:</emphasis> This value is not a limit for each
                Application Server but a value used by the load
                balancing algorithm as we'll see later.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Redirection name of this
                server:</emphasis> this is used to launch
                session. When you launch a session, you are redirected
                to an Application server using the redirection name as
                redirection. In some cases the default redirection
                name (the FQDN you gave at the ApS installation) is
                not valid. For instance, if you setup an private IP
                address and you want to connect from Internet.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Web port of this server:</emphasis> This
            is the port where the Application Server listen for
            webserices access from the Session Manager</para>.
            <important>
              <para>You shouldn't modify this value unless you are
              sure of what you are doing</para>
            </important>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
              The maintenance/production is a status. This status is
              used to keep some servers online and ready to use on
              maintenance to be sure that no sessions are going to be
              launch. It's usefull when perfoming software upgrade for
              instance.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
          On the Linux application, it's possible to install
          applications directly from console by giving a package name.
          It's also possible to ask for upgrade the server. It'll
          upgrade the applications and the Ulteo software.
        </para>
      </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Unregistered servers page</title>

      <para>
	An Application server is unregistered
	untill an admin registers it by clicking
	the <emphasis>register button</emphasis>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tasks page</title>

      <para>
        This is only available on Linux server yet. A tasks is a
        request to a Application Server to install/remove an
        application as we talked in the servers page.
      </para>

      <para>
        This page just list the known tasks with their status.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Shared folders page</title>

      <para>
        Shared folders is a feature to allow members of users groups
        to work together on a virtual drive.
      </para>
      <para>
        To make it work, create one, add some users groups to this
        start a session.
      </para>
      <important>
        <para>
          You have to turn it on the Shared folder for session by
          clicking on the button on the Shared folder page.
        </para>
      </important>

      <para>
        This page just list the known tasks with their status.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Users</title>
    <para>
      This category is about the user and the users groups.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each user is shown with his login, his display name, his uid and
      all other extra fields from the user database.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can get more information about a User either by clicking
      the <emphasis>Manage</emphasis> button or by clicking on the
      user login hyperlink.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Users page</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="img/admin-console/servers.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <section>
      <title>Manage a user</title>
      <para>
	In this page, we can modify each user attribute if the user database is writable. 
	Actually, only MySQL module is writable.
      </para>
      <para>
	There is also the list of user groups that contain this user and the list of active sessions for this user.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>User Group Management</title>
      <para>
	This page provides a list of user group with their name, their
	description and their status (Enabled or Block).  You also
	can add and remove user groups.
      </para>

      <para>
	The Manage page of a specific group lets you change status and
	description.  It's also possible to add or remove users from a
	specific group and view the list of publications for a
	specific group.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Applications Management</title>
    <para>
      This page shows the list of applications which are (physically)
      installed on the application servers.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each application is shown with his name, his description and his
      type (Linux or Windows).
    </para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Applications page</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="img/admin-console/applications.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      You can have more information about an application either by
      clicking the <emphasis>Manage</emphasis> button or by clicking
      on the application name hyperlink.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Manage an application</title>
      <para>
	When you manage an application, you can add or remove this
	application from online servers and from the application
	groups.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Application group Management</title>
      <para>
	This page provides a list of application groups with their
	name, their description and their status (Enabled or Blocked).
	You can also add and remove application groups.
      </para>

      <para>
	The manage page of a specific group lets you change the status
	and the description.  It's also possible to add or remove
	users from a specific group and view the list of publications
	for a specific group.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Static applications page</title>
      <para>
        Static application are application that have not be detected
	automatically on an Application Server.
        It's set directly on the console. It could be w Web
	application for instance.
      </para>
    </section>


    <section>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <para>
	This page shows associations between user groups and
	application groups. A publication wizard is available to make
	the process simple.
      </para>
      <para>
	This wizard is in 3 main steps:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>selection of users</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>selection of applications</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>confirmations</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
	If you choose users from the user list instead of an existing
	user group, the system is going to ask you for a user group
	name and description. It's the same for application selection.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Configuration</title>
    <para>
      At this page, you can configure your sesion manager.
    </para>
    <para>
      Be careful when you change the config, it can break actives
      session depending on the kind of action.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Configuration page</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="img/admin-console/configuration.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <section>
      <title>Database settings page</title>
      <para>
        In this page, it's possible to change the information the
	MySQL database used by the OVD.
      </para>
      <important>
        <para>
          If you change informations on this page, you can break your
          system, delete your users groups or other information.
        </para>
      </important>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>System settings page</title>
      <para>
        In this page, it's possible to customize the language of the
        console.
        It's also possible to change the admin policy for OVD users.
      </para>

      <section>
        <title>Policy</title>
        <para>
          By modifying the policy, you authorized each of your OVD
          users to perform some admin actions.  It's a default policy,
          it's can be override by customize the policy for a users
          group.
        </para>
        <para>
          For instance, if you select <emphasis>user admin
          panel</emphasis>, you authorizing every OVD users to logon
          the admin console.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>
            We advice to keep disable all field of the default policy.
          </para>
          </note>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Server settings page</title>
      <para>
        This page is about the Applications servers settings.
      </para>

      <simplesect>
        <title>Load balancing</title>
        <para>
          The load balancing is used to choose the server to use when
          a user request for a session. It's possible to customize the
          algorithm to change the priority of the criterians.
        </para>
      </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Profile settings page</title>
      <para>
        Ulteo OVD can be plugged to LDAP or Active Directory or keep
        is own local database.
      </para>
    </section>


    <section>
      <title>Session Configuration</title>
      <para>
        This part is about the default configuration of the session
        and what the user can force.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Events Configuration</title>
      <para>
        In this page, you can give email adress to receive alert when
        events occurs.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Web interface settings page</title>
      <para>
        This page is about the configuration of the Ulteo OVD main
        page (the one you use to start sessions).
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Status Category</title>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Status page</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="img/admin-console/status.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <section>
      <title>Session page</title>
      <para>
	This page shows a list of active sessions with the following information:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="strong">Session:</emphasis> the session id</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="strong">Server:</emphasis> the server where the session runs</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="strong">User:</emphasis> the user which started the session</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
	It's possible to end a session by clicking the <emphasis>Kill</emphasis> button.
      </para>

      <para>
	You can have more information about a session by clicking on the session id.
      </para>

      <section>
	<title>Manage a session</title>
	<para>
	  On the general page, there are two additional features:
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>The date when the session started</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>A button to join the session using the desktop sharing system</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
      </section>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Logs page</title>
    <para>
      This page show the log on the Session Manager. The log level
      depends on the configuration set in the Configuration System
      settings page.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reporting page</title>
    <para>
      This page give you a report of you OVD infrastructure in a time
      window you select.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Summary page</title>
    <para>
      Ths summary page show all links between user, users groups,
      applications, applications groups and server.
    </para>
    <para>
      This page is very usefull when you are lost in the publication
      or when you don't why you can't start sessions.
    </para>
    <important>
      <para>
        This page can take time to load if you have many users in your
        database. Use it carrefully.
      </para>
    </important>
  </section>
  </section>

</article>
