<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Ulteo Open Virtual Desktop v@VERSION@</title>

    <subtitle>Architecture Overview</subtitle>

    <graphic align="center" fileref="img/ovd.png"/>

    <copyright>
      <year>@YEAR@</year>

      <holder>Ulteo SAS - <ulink url="http://www.ulteo.com"/></holder>
    </copyright>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>The purpose of this documentation is to provide a high-level
  description of the architecture typically used in an <emphasis>Ulteo Open
  Virtual Desktop</emphasis> server farm.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Servers Roles</title>

    <para>A typical Ulteo OVD installation uses several servers with different
    roles. Some of the server roles are required and others are
    optional.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Session Manager</title>

      <para>This server is the central piece of an Ulteo OVD server farm and
      always required. It manages the session establishment from a client and
      hosts the administration console. The Session Manager should be
      installed prior to any other server.</para>

      <para>Ulteo provides various Linux packages for installing the Session
      Manager on a Linux server. It should also be possible to install and run
      the Session Manager on Windows, but this must be done directly from the
      available source code. Ulteo does not provide a Windows
      installer.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Application Server</title>

      <para>Ulteo OVD is an application and desktop delivery solution. The
      Application Server in the OVD solution is the server that hosts the
      applications and is accessed from the client using a remote display
      protocol.</para>

      <para>The Application Server can be either a Linux system or a Windows
      system depending on the type of applications or desktop you want to
      deliver. Of course, you can mix Linux and Windows machines in an Ulteo
      OVD farm to deliver applications from different systems.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Web Portal</title>

      <para>This Web Portal server is responsible for managing browser-based
      client sessions. In OVD 4, there are 2 types of browser-based sessions.
      The first type of browser session uses a Java applet within the browser
      to communicate with the Web Portal. In this case, the Web Portal
      supplies the Java applet if it is not already available in the browser.
      The second type of browser session requires an HTML5 compliant browser
      on the client machine, no software will be installed on the client
      machine. In both cases, the OVD session is tunneled over an SSL session.
      In addition, the OVD Web Portal provides capabilities for other web
      sites to integrate with OVD.</para>

      <para>Users may decide to use one of the Ulteo OVD Native Clients to
      create an OVD session instead of using a web browser. In that case, the
      Web Portal would not be required.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Web Applications</title>

      <para>An OVD server may be configured to support Web Application
      Integration. This could be installed as a standalone server or could be
      configured on an existing server with different roles. The Web
      Application Integration provides seamless integration of Web
      Applications into the OVD environment and a Single Sign On
      capability</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>File Server</title>

      <para>Within the Ulteo OVD application and desktop delivery solution,
      the File Server provides a centralized file management system that
      enables users to access the same files independently of which
      application server is used to provide the application. This software
      manages a network file system that the Application Servers access when
      users are running sessions. It hosts both user profiles and data files
      and folders.</para>

      <para>The File Server is currently provided for Linux based servers
      only. In a small OVD server farm, the File Server may reside on the same
      physical machine as the Application Server. In larger installations, the
      File Server would typically run on dedicated hardware.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Gateway</title>

      <para>Ulteo OVD uses several ports during the client session, mainly
      HTTPS (443) and RDP (3389). But in some cases, for example when the user
      is remote, a firewall would typically be configured to block access to
      the RDP port. The Gateway also can be used to unify access to multiple
      Application Servers by providing a single point of access to the
      clients.</para>

      <para>The Gateway tunnels all the OVD connections over an HTTPS session.
      So from anywhere, users that have access to HTTPS (443), will also be
      able to start an Ulteo OVD session.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Subsystem</title>

    <para>The Subsystem is an archive built and delivered by Ulteo containing
    an Application Server, a File Server and a typical Ulteo desktop
    pre-installed. It is the easiest way to setup a demo architecture. It can
    be installed on any Linux distribution supported by Ulteo.</para>

    <para>The subsystem archive can be downloaded when the Session Manager has
    been installed in order to simplify the deployement of Linux OVD
    Application Servers.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Overview ports and protocols</title>

    <para>The following diagram presents an overview of ports and protocols
    used in <emphasis>Ulteo Open Virtual Desktop</emphasis>.</para>

    <screenshot id="protocole_overview">
      <screeninfo>Ports and protocols</screeninfo>

      <graphic fileref="img/ports_protocols.png"
               id="protocole_overview_graphic"/>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="colophon.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
</article>
