<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Ulteo Open Virtual Desktop v@VERSION@</title>
    <subtitle>Architecture Overview</subtitle>
    <graphic fileref="img/ovd.png" align="center"/>

    <copyright>
      <year>@YEAR@</year>
      <holder>Ulteo SAS - <ulink url="http://www.ulteo.com" /></holder>
    </copyright>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>
    The purpose of this documentation is to describe the architecture
    of an <emphasis>Ulteo Open Virtual Desktop</emphasis> server farm.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Servers types and softwares</title>

    <para>
      Ulteo OVD uses several servers with different roles. Part of them
      are required and the others are optional.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Session Manager</title>
      <para>
        This server is the central piece of an Ulteo OVD
        architecture. It manages the session launching and hosts the
        administration console. It is the first software to install.
      </para>
      <para>
        The Session Manager can only be installed on Linux using a
        package at the moment, but it is also possible to run it on
        Windows by installing it from sources.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Application Server</title>
      <para>
        Ulteo OVD is an application and desktop delivery solution
        so there are some servers which hosts the applications and can
        be accessed using a remote display solution.
      </para>
      <para>
        This server can be running on a Linux system or on a Windows system
        depending on the type of applications or desktop you want
        to deliver. Of course, you can mix Linux and Windows machines
        in an Ulteo OVD farm to deliver applications from
        different systems.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Web Client</title>
      <para>
        This software is used for start an Ulteo OVD session without
        installing anything on the client machine, only a web
        browser is required. This is not the only way to start a session, you
        can also use the Ulteo OVD Native Client. So this software
        is not required in an Ulteo OVD farm.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>File Server</title>
      <para>
        Ulteo OVD is an application and desktop delivery solution
        but it can be useful to have a centralized file system
        management to ensure user access to the same files when
        using applications from different servers. This software
        manages a network file system that the Application Server
        access when users are running sessions. It hosts both user profiles
        and shared folders.
      </para>
      <para>
        The File Server can only be installed on Linux for now. It is
        possible to install it on the same machine as an Application
        Server.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Gateway</title>
      <para>
        Ulteo OVD uses several ports during the session, mainly
        HTTPS (443) and RDP (3389). But in some places, when the user is mobile,
        some firewalls are blocking access to those ports. Another possible
        issue is to have several public IP address for each server.
      </para>
      <para>
        The Gateway tunnelize all the OVD connections into an HTTPS
        link. So from anywhere you can have access to HTTPS (443),
        it will be possible to start Ulteo OVD sessions.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Subsystem</title>

    <para>
      The Subsystem is an archive built and delivered by Ulteo
      containing an Application Server, a File Server and an Ulteo
      typical desktop pre-installed. It is the easiest way to setup a
      demo architecture. It can be installed on any supported Linux
      distribution.
    </para>

    <para>
      This subsystem archive can be downloaded when the Session Manager
      is installed in order to simplify the deployement of Linux OVD
      Application Servers.
    </para>
  </section>

<!--
  <section>
    <title>High Availability / Failover</title>

    <para>
      As the Session Manager is the main piece of the Ulteo OVD farm,
      it requires to have a failover solution to avoid having a broken farm
      when the Session Manager has a problem.
    </para>
    <para>
      This High Availability solution uses Heartbeat, a solution used by the Linux HA
      project.
    </para>
  </section>
-->
  <xi:include href="colophon.xml" />
</article>
