<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Ulteo Open Virtual Desktop v@VERSION@</title>
    <subtitle>Internationalization and Localization</subtitle>
    <graphic fileref="img/ovd.png" align="center"/>

    <copyright>
      <year>@YEAR@</year>
      <holder>Ulteo SAS - <ulink url="http://www.ulteo.com" /></holder>
    </copyright>
  </articleinfo>

  <section id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      There is more than one language in the world and
      many people do not speak English. This documentation explains
      how Ulteo take care about internationalization and
      localization into the Open Virtual Desktop solution.
    </para>

    <para>
      Firstly, Ulteo is translated in many languages and is
      opened to support any new one.
    </para>
    <para>
      Secondly, as Ulteo software is a solution to access to desktops
      and applications, the client can specify the requested language
      for the session. But different operating systems and
      applications have to support these different languages.
    </para>
    <para>
      Finally, the user needs to use the local keyboard and, there is
      more than one keyboard layout in the world. Ulteo solutions
      support different behavior for keyboard mapping between clients
      and servers.
    </para>
  </section>


  <section id="translations">
    <title>Ulteo OVD translations</title>
    <para>
      Two parts of the Ulteo OVD solution are translated: the
      Administration Console and the client softwares.
    </para>
    
    <note>
      <para>
        The Ulteo OVD translations are freely provided by the
        community.
      </para>
      <para>
        If your own language is lacking in the current Ulteo OVD
        translations and you are motivated to translate solutions, you
        are very welcome and contact us at this address:
        <email>translations@ulteo.com</email>.
      </para>
    </note>

    <section id="translations_admin">
      <title>Administration Console</title>

      <para>
        The default behavior of the Administration Console is to
        detect the client browser language. But it's also possible to
        force your language if you prefer: from the
        <emphasis>Configuration</emphasis> page, go into
        <emphasis>System settings</emphasis> and change the
        <emphasis>Administration Console language</emphasis> option.
      </para>

      <important id="admin_console_important">
        <para>
          After the language setting, the console could still
          be in English. That's probably because your Linux server
          system hosting the Session Manager does not support the
          new language. So you have to add the language
          support and restart the HTTP server.
        </para>
        <para>
          Each Linux distribution has his own method to manage
          language support. For instance, on Ubuntu system, it's a
          <emphasis>language-pack-$LANG</emphasis> package to
          install.
        </para>
      </important>

      <para>
        On the technical side, the Session Manager translations are
        provided by the <emphasis>ulteo-ovd-l10n</emphasis>
        package. This package contain both clients and Administration
        Console translations into GNU Gettext files.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="translations_web_client">
      <title>Ulteo Web Client</title>

      <para>
        At the first connexion, the Web Client detects the client
        language from the browser settings. But you can modify it by
        clicking on <emphasis>Advanced Settings</emphasis> and modify
        the <emphasis>Language</emphasis> option. When the option is
        manually set by the user, it is stored into a COOKIE and is
        re-use the selected language at next connections.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The Web Client uses the same translation system than the Session
        Manager Administration Console. So please <ulink
        url="#admin_console_important">the Administration Console
        note</ulink> part if you encounter any problem.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="translations_native_client">
      <title>Ulteo Native Client</title>
      <para>
        When the Native Clients started up, it detect the system
        language and apply the translation if possible. It is
        also possible to modify it manually by clicking on
        <emphasis>More options</emphasis> and modify the
        <emphasis>Language</emphasis> option.
      </para>

      <para>
        When the option is manually set by the user, the selected
        language is saved into a configuration file to keep your
        setting for the next start of the Native Client. So it is also
        possible to force the client language by editing the
        setting file.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="aps">
    <title>Application Servers</title>
    <para>
      You are probably interested in starting non-English Ulteo
      sessions on your OVD farm. Either because your users do not
      speak English or users speak different (various) languages. Of
      course, it is possible to select a language from the Ulteo
      Client but the Application Server operating system must support
      the selected language.
    </para>

    <para>
      By default, both <trademark
      class="registered">Windows</trademark> and Linux supports
      English language. According to) the installation medium, it can
      support another language out-of-the-box.  And, once installed,
      it is still possible to add other languages support. But the
      process is different between Linux and <trademark
      class="registered">Windows</trademark>.
    </para>

    <section id="aps_linux">
      <title>Linux</title>

      <para>
        Linux is a complete multilingual Operating System. The
        packaging system provides translations pack for both system and
        applications.
      </para>

      <para>
        The Linux subsystem archive does not support any other language
        than English on a new install.
      </para>
      <para>
        To install a language support, you have to install some
        packages.
      </para>
      <screen>
        <![CDATA[
# apt-get install language-pack-$LANG]]>
      </screen>
      <para>
        To have a full language support for all
        applications, there are some other packages to install.
      </para>
      <screen>
        <![CDATA[
# apt-get install language-pack-$LANG \
                  language-support-$LANG \
                  language-pack-gnome-$LANG \
                  language-pack-kde-$LANG \
                  kde-l10n-$LANG \
                  openoffice.org-l10n-$LANG]]>
      </screen>
    </section>

    <section id="aps_windows">
      <title><trademark class="registered">Windows</trademark></title>
      <para>
        The <trademark class="registered">Microsoft
        Windows</trademark> server 2003 and 2008 are installed in a
        specific language but alternative languages could be
        installed.
      </para>

      <para>
        The process is different from <trademark
        class="registered">Windows</trademark> server 2003 and 2008
        (r2) but, for both systems, you have to get MUI language packs from
        <trademark class="registered">Microsoft</trademark> website.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <trademark class="registered">Windows</trademark> 2003
            language packs are installable from a setup program (one
            for each language). So select the language and execute the
            setup.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            For <trademark class="registered">Windows</trademark>
            2008, you have to go into the <emphasis>Control
            Panel</emphasis>, then <emphasis>Region and
            Language</emphasis>, select the <emphasis>Keyboards and
            Languages</emphasis> tab and click on
            <emphasis>Install/Uninstall Language</emphasis>. Then you
            just have to browse to the <emphasis>lp.cab</emphasis> and
            select it.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <simplesect>
        <title>Applications</title>
        <para>
          On <trademark class="registered">Microsoft
          Windows</trademark>, each application manage its own
          internationalization system. Some applications can be
          installed in multilingual mode whereas some others supports only
          one language.
        </para>

        <para>
          For instance, Microsoft Office include only one language as
          default afer the installation. But you can add language packs
          separatly. The same process is also possible with OpenOffice
          and many others applications.
        </para>
      </simplesect>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="keyboard">
    <title>Keyboards layouts</title>
    
    <para>
      Ulteo supports two type on input method: scancode and unicode.
    </para>

    <section id="keyboard_scancode">
      <title>Scancode</title>

      <para>
        Scancode is a database where, from each keyboard layout, each
        keyboard key has a different code. So the client sends the
        keyboard layout identifier at session start and transform each
        keyboard input key into a scancode that is sent to the RDP
        server.
      </para>

      <para>
        This method is the default method used into Ulteo OVD.
      </para>

      <para>
        The problem of this method is that each client and server have
        to know the specifications of any existing keyboard layout in
        the world ... which is not possible. So there is a set of the
        most popular used keyboard included in the client.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="keyboard_unicode">
      <title>Unicode</title>

      <para>
        Unicode is an alternative method that send to client unicode
        characters instead of keyboard key codes that saving server to
        transform and manage each keyboard input.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="keyboard_choose">
      <title>Choosing the method and/or the keyboard layout</title>

      <para>
        By default, on both Native Client and Web Client, the scancode
        method is set and the keyboard layout is auto detected on the
        system. But, it's also possible to select it manually by
        clicking on <emphasis>Advanced Settings</emphasis> and change
        the <emphasis>Keyboard layout</emphasis> option.
      </para>

      <para>
        The choosen keyboard layout is stored into the default
        configuration file for the Native Client (default.conf) and
        into a Cookie for the WebClient.
      </para>

      <para>
        If the scancode method doesn't support your own keyboard
        layout, you can try to enable the Unicode input method. To do
        that, you have to set the <emphasis>input-method =
        unicode</emphasis> option into the configuration file for the
        Native Client configuration. Or uncomment the
        <emphasis>define('RDP_INPUT_METHOD', 'unicode');</emphasis>
        line into the <emphasis>config.inc.php</emphasis> file for the
        WebClient.
      </para>

      <para>
        In consequence, you won't see the keyboard layout switcher option
        anymore in the client interface.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
