<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Ulteo Open Virtual Desktop v@VERSION@</title>
    <subtitle>Web Client</subtitle>
    <graphic fileref="img/ovd.png" align="center"/>

    <copyright>
      <year>@YEAR@</year>
      <holder>Ulteo SAS - <ulink url="http://www.ulteo.com" /></holder>
    </copyright>
  </articleinfo>

  <section id="intro">
    <title id="intro_title">Introduction</title>

    <para>
	  This documentation describes how to use the Ulteo Open Virtual Desktop "Web Client", its capabilities and how to launch Ulteo OVD sessions using a web client.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="prerequisites">
    <title id="prerequisites_title">Prerequisites</title>

    <para>
      This is not the Web Portal installation documentation. You need to have already installed a Web Portal to be able to launch Ulteo OVD web client sessions.
    </para>

    <xi:include href="common.xml" xpointer="system_requirements_client" />
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>User Interface</title>

    <para>
	  Ulteo OVD provides support for HTML5 client compliant web browsers and also a Java applet. The user may decide when starting a session
	  whether to use the HTML5 or Java client. When launching a new OVD session, the environment is validated to determine 
	  if the browser can support the Java applet. If the requirements are not met, then the Java option is disabled.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Web Portal - Test window</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="img/wc_test_window.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      If the test fails and the browser is not HTML5 compliant, you will see this window.
      It means that your web browser does not have the required functional Java support, or no Java support at all.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Web Portal - Test failed</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="img/wc_test_failed.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      When the tests are completed successfully, you have access to the login window that you will use to launch your session.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Web Portal - Login window</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="img/wc_login_window.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      You can now enter your username in the list, type your password, click the "Connect" button and voilà!
    </para>

    <screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Web Portal - Desktop session</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="img/wc_desktop_session.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Advanced Settings</title>

    <para>
      In the login window, you can set advanced parameters by clicking the "Advanced settings" button.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Web Portal - Advanced login window</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="img/wc_advanced_login_window.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      As you can see, you now have several options, each one is described below.
    </para>

    <simplesect id="advanced_settings">
      <title>Advanced Settings Description</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Use local credentials:</emphasis> When enabled, the Web Client will send a request to the Session Manager containg your current machine's credentials, using for example Kerberos or NTLM. When disabled, the Web Client will send a request to the Session Manager containing the login and password entered in the login window.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Mode:</emphasis> This option allows you to pick which session mode you want to use.
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Desktop:</emphasis> Launch a full desktop with applications integrated inside it.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Portal:</emphasis> Launch a web portal with applications listed in it. Applications in this mode are launched seamlessly.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Type:</emphasis> This option allows you to switch between HTML5 or Java
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Java:</emphasis> Launch a session using the Java applet
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>HTML5:</emphasis> Launch a session using an HTML5 compliant browser
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Language:</emphasis> This option allows you to pick which language your OVD session will use. Changing the language will auto-pick the associated keyboard layout (see below).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Keyboard layout:</emphasis> This option allows you to select which keyboard layout your local keyboard is using.
          </para>
        </listitem>        
      </itemizedlist>
    </simplesect>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Starting A Session</title>

    <para>
      When you start a session, a splash screen appears indicating that the session is loading.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Web Portal - Session loading</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="img/wc_session_loading.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      Below you will find screenshots for both Desktop and Portal mode.
    </para>

    <simplesect>
      <title>Desktop Session</title>

      <para>
        When the session is ready, your Desktop is available and you can launch applications, explore your files etc.
      </para>

      <screenshot>
	    <screeninfo>Web Portal - Desktop session</screeninfo>
	    <graphic fileref="img/wc_desktop_session.png"></graphic>
      </screenshot>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
      <title>Portal Session</title>

      <para>
        When the session is ready, your Portal is available and you can launch applications seamlessly.
      </para>

      <screenshot>
	    <screeninfo>Web Portal - Portal session</screeninfo>
	    <graphic fileref="img/wc_portal_session.png"></graphic>
      </screenshot>
    </simplesect>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Session End</title>

    <para>
      When you leave your Ulteo OVD session, you will see this window.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Web Portal - Session end</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="img/wc_session_end.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      Clicking to start another session gets you back to the login window.
    </para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="colophon.xml" />
</article>
