<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Ulteo Open Virtual Desktop v@VERSION@</title>
    <subtitle>Web Client</subtitle>
    <graphic fileref="img/ovd.png" align="center"/>

    <copyright>
      <year>@YEAR@</year>
      <holder>Ulteo SAS - <ulink url="http://www.ulteo.com" /></holder>
    </copyright>
  </articleinfo>

  <section id="intro">
    <title id="intro_title">Introduction</title>

    <para>
	  This documentation aims to describe the usage of Ulteo Open Virtual Desktop "Web Client" in its capabilities and how to launch Ulteo OVD sessions with it.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="prerequisites">
    <title id="prerequisites_title">Prerequisites</title>

    <para>
      This is not a Web Client installation documentation. You need to have already installed a Web Client to be able to launch Ulteo OVD sessions with it.
    </para>

    <xi:include href="common.xml" xpointer="system_requirements_client" />
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>User interface</title>

    <para>
      When you start using a Web Client, some tests are done to see if your browser can launch OVD sessions successfully, you will see this window.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Web Client - Test window</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="img/wc_test_window.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      If the test fails, you will see this window, it means that your web browser does not have a working Java support, or no Java support at all.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Web Client - Test failed</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="img/wc_test_failed.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      When the tests are done and successful, you have access to the login window that you will use to launch your session.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Web Client - Login window</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="img/wc_login_window.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      You just have to pick your username in the list, type your password, click the "Connect" button and voilà!
    </para>

    <screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Web Client - Desktop session</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="img/wc_desktop_session.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Advanced settings</title>

    <para>
      At the login window, you can set advanced parameters by clicking the "Advanced settings" button.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Web Client - Advanced login window</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="img/wc_advanced_login_window.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      As you can see, you now have more available options, each one is described below.
    </para>

    <simplesect id="advanced_settings">
      <title>Advanced settings description</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Use local credentials:</emphasis> When enabled, the Web Client will request the Session Manager with your current machine's credentials, using for example Kerberos or NTLM. When disabled, the Web Client will request the Session Manager with the login and password entered in the login window.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Mode:</emphasis> This option allows you to pick which session mode you want to use.
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Desktop:</emphasis> Launch a full desktop with applications integrated inside it.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <emphasis>Portal:</emphasis> Launch a web portal with applications listed in it. Applications are launched seamlessly.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Language:</emphasis> This option allows you to pick which language your OVD session will use. Changing the language will auto-pick the associated keyboard layout (see below).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Keyboard layout:</emphasis> This option allows you to select which keyboard layout your local keyboard is using.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Use pop-up:</emphasis> Whether to launch your OVD session in a new browser window, or in the current one.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </simplesect>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Start a session</title>

    <para>
      When you start a session, a loading splash appears.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Web Client - Session loading</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="img/wc_session_loading.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      Below you will find screenshots for both Desktop and Portal mode.
    </para>

    <simplesect>
      <title>Desktop session</title>

      <para>
        When the session is ready, your Desktop is available and you can launch applications, explore your files...
      </para>

      <screenshot>
	    <screeninfo>Web Client - Desktop session</screeninfo>
	    <graphic fileref="img/wc_desktop_session.png"></graphic>
      </screenshot>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
      <title>Portal session</title>

      <para>
        When the session is ready, your Portal is available and you can launch applications seamlessly.
      </para>

      <screenshot>
	    <screeninfo>Web Client - Portal session</screeninfo>
	    <graphic fileref="img/wc_portal_session.png"></graphic>
      </screenshot>
    </simplesect>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Session end</title>

    <para>
      When you leave your Ulteo OVD session, you will see this window.
    </para>

    <screenshot>
	  <screeninfo>Web Client - Session end</screeninfo>
	  <graphic fileref="img/wc_session_end.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      Clicking to start another session gets you back to the login window.
    </para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="colophon.xml" />
</article>
